<chapter title="Writing Pike Modules">
  <p>
    This chapter will discuss how to extend Pike by writing
    modules. There are two major ways to write modules, either they
    can be written in Pike, or they can be written in C. Generally,
    modules can be seen as a collection of pike programs and
    functions. This is, obviously, handy for grouping related programs
    and functions.
  </p>

  <p>
    A pike module is actually a pike program which is cloned by the
    pike compiler during compilation of programs. This means that all
    lfuns that can be used in a pike program also can be used in a
    module. This is, for instance, useful for overloading the
    operators of a module to obtain a certain behaviour. Bear in mind
    that variables defined on a module-wide bases are shared among all
    clones of programs in the module.
    <fixme>Explain difference between .pmod and .pike</fixme>
  </p>

  <p>
    Pike searches for modules in the module path as defined during the
    compilation of a pike program. The module-path defaults to contain
    the directory where all standard pike modules are installed. This
    can be altered using
    <ref>/master.CompatResolver()->add_module_path()</ref> in a
    program or by letting the environment variable
    <b>PIKE_MODULE_PATH</b> contain a colon-separated list of
    directories to be searched for modules before looking at the
    default location. 
  </p>

  <section title="Writing Modules in Pike">
    <p>
      Writing modules in pike is by far the easiest way to extend
      pike. They are also useful for structuring a larger programming
      project into different source files.
    </p>

    <p>
      There are two ways of create a pike module written in
      pike. Either create a file named as the module will be called
      with the extension <expr>.pmod</expr> and place all program and
      function definitions in it. The other way, which usually is more
      flexible, is to create a directory named as the module with the
      extension <expr>.pmod</expr> and place all program definitions
      (<expr>.pike</expr>-files) within this directory. If a file called
      <expr>module.pmod</expr> is placed in the directory the function and
      program definitions within it will be merged with the programs
      found in the directory. This file could, as an example, be used
      to specify functions residing in the module, while programs in
      the module are placed in <expr>.pike</expr>-files.
    </p>

    <p>
      Note that Pike modules must not use try to load files relative to
      __FILE__, since such code will break in Microsoft Windows.
      <fixme>Explain why.</fixme>
    </p>
 
 </section>
  
  <section title="Writing Modules in C">
    <p><fixme>To be written.</fixme></p>

    <subsection title="Practical details">
      <p>First of all your module needs a Makefile.in file. It need not be
         more complicated than the following example:
<pre>
# &#36;Id&#36;
@make_variables@
VPATH=@srcdir@:@srcdir@/../..:../..
OBJS=
MODULE_LDFLAGS=@LDFLAGS@ @LIBS@

CONFIG_HEADERS=@CONFIG_HEADERS@

@dynamic_module_makefile@
@dependencies@
</pre></p>

      <p>A few customizations must however be done. The <tt>OBJS</tt> variable should
         contain all the object files produced in your module. You should
         add to the <tt>MODULE_LDFLAGS</tt> variable all the needed <tt>-L&lt;libdir&gt; -R&lt;libdir&gt;</tt>
         options followed by all the needed <tt>-l&lt;lib&gt;</tt> options. If you want your
         module to always be linked statically, change <tt>@dynamic_module_makefile@</tt>
         to <tt>@static_module_makefile@</tt>. Normally you do not need to manually add
         any dependencies to Makefile.in.</p>

     <p>There must be a testsuite.in file in the modules directory, even if it
        only is an empty file.</p>

     <p>You should have a configure.in file for your module and it should test
        for all features that you need. Do not trust the global configure tests
        to do thing for you. Further, your configure.in should contain the line
        <tt>sinclude(../module_configuration.in)</tt>.</p>

     <p>All C/C++ files should include <tt>"global.h"</tt> as the first included file. It
        is also good if they contain <tt>RCSID(&#36;Id&#36;)</tt>.</p>

     <p>When building your module for the first time you need to:
        <ol>
        <li>run autoconf</li>
        <li>do "make depend" from your build dir</li>
        <li>re-run configure from your build dir</li>
        <li>run make in your build dir</li>
        </ol></p>

    </subsection>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Special Module Variables and functions">
    There are a few variables and functions that have a special
    meaning in a module. 
    
    <subsection title="_module_value">
      <p>
	If <expr>_module_value</expr> is non-zero it will be used as
	the value of the module. <expr>_module_value</expr> has to be of
	a type which is indicable, ie. an object, mapping or
	multiset.
      </p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection title="The indexing operator">
      <p>
	If a <ref>lfun::`[]</ref> is defined in a module it will be
	called when the module is indexed using the .-operator. 
      </p>
    </subsection>
  </section>
  
</chapter>